Register of the C.R.B. Educational Foundation Records, 1920-1956
Hoover Institution Archives
C.R.B. Educational Foundation Records,
1920-1956
46005
C.R.B. Educational Foundation
7 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 5 envelopes, 1 stack of oversize charts (3.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Reports, minutes of meetings, correspondence, charts, clippings, other printed matter, and photographs, relating to Belgian-American exchange fellowships sponsored by the foundation, Belgian-American cultural relations, child health and nutrition in Belgium, the German occupation of Belgium in World War II, Kings Albert I and Leopold III of Belgium, and the 1950 Belgian plebiscite on the restoration of the monarchy.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (7 reels).
Access Points
Leopold III, King of the Belgians, 1901-; Albert I, King of the Belgians, 1875-1934.; Education--Belgium.; Education.; Belgium--Relations--United States.; United States--Relations--Belgium.; Plebiscite--Belgium.; Scholarships--Belgium.; Scholarships--United States.; Students, Interchange of.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Belgium.; Belgium.; Belgium--History--German occupation, 1940-1945.; Belgium--Politics and government--1914-1951.; United States--Foreign relations.; Child welfare--Belgium.; Commission for Relief in Belgium (1914-1930)
Historical Note
The C.R.B. Educational Foundation was endowed from residual funds of the Commission for Relief in Belgium. Its operations included the sponsoring of Belgian-American exchange fellowships, the fostering of Belgian-American cultural relations, and aid to child health and nutrition programs in Belgium.
In 1938, the C.R.B. Educational Foundation changed its name to Belgian-American Educational Foundation.
Series Description
- OFFICE FILE, 1915-1940 (Boxes 1-2)
  Correspondence, memoranda, minutes of meetings, printed matter and other material, relating to operations of the C.R.B. Educational Foundation, which changed its name to Belgian American Educational Foundation in 1938. Arranged by physical form
- REPORTS, 1921-1956 (Boxes 3-6)
  Reports arranged alphabetically by title
- CLIPPINGS, 1928-1947 (Boxes 6-7)
  Clippings arranged by subject
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS, 1930s(?) (Box 8)
  Flemish flags, education, health and nutrition questionnaires and statistical data
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1915-1941 (Photo file)
  10 prints depicting C.R.B. reunion and staff in Brussels, war damage in Belgium, and ship "Camino" docked at Rotterdam. Arranged by subject
Container List
- OFFICE FILE, 1915-1940
  - Agreement with Stanford University, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Brochures describing the C.R.B. Educational Foundation, 1920, 1922 (Folder 2)
  - Certificates of incorporation and by-laws, 1935, 1939 (Folder 3)
  - Correspondence
    - American Library Service, 1936 (Folder 4)
    - Barnes, Julius, 1924-1925 (Folder 5)
    - Chandler, Harry, 1924 (Folder 6)
    - Fisher, Harold H., 1935 (Folder 7)
    - Galpin, Perrin, 1934-1939 (Folder 8)
    - Heupgen, Georges, 1936 (Folder 9)
    - Hoagland, H. V., 1935 (Folder 10)
    - Hoover, Herbert C., 1934-1939 (Folder 11)
    - National Efficiency Society, 1920 (Folder 12)
    - Reinhart, G. F., 1938 (Folder 13)
    - Rickard, Edgar, 1934 (Folder 14)
    - Roman, Jules, 1935 (Folder 15)
    - Sexson, Paul, 1935-1936 (Folder 16)
    - Taylor, Alonzo, 1924 (Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 18)
  - Envelopes made out of military maps (Folder 19)
  - Financial records, 1934-1936 (Folder 20)
  - Minutes of meetings
    - Executive Committee
      - 1937 March 22 (Folder 21)
      - 1938
        - May 12 (Folder 22)
        - September 13 (Folder 23)
        - October 28 (Folder 24)
        - December 6 (Folder 25)
      - 1939
        - Mar 9 (Folder 26)
        - May 11 (Folder 27)
        - September 26 (Folder 28)
      - 1940 September 25 (Folder 29)
    - Members and directors
      - 1920 December 1 (Folder 30)
      - 1925 December 1 (Folder 31)
      - 1938 December 6 (Folder 32)
      - 1939 December 5 (Folder 33)
  - Postmaster receipts for mail sacks, 1939 December (Folder 34)
  - Printed matter (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Subject file
    - Belgian-American fellowships, 1938-1940 (Folder 2)
    - Belgian franc, Devaluation of, 1923 (Folder 3)
    - Belgian Orphan Fund (Folder 4)
    - Belgium - History - German occupation, 1918-1918. German military regulations in Brussels, 1915 (Folder 5)
    - Belgium - History - German occupation, 1940-1945. Ville de Namur, "Communications de l'administration communale," 1940 (Folder 6)
    - C.R.B. Reunion Dinners
      - 20th anniversary, 1934 October 22 (Folder 7)
      - 25th anniversary, 1939 October 28 (Folder 8)
    - Leopold III, King of Belgium (Folder 9-11)
    - Louvain University Library, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Warehouse storage contract, Dunham and Reid, 1939 (Folder 2)
- REPORTS, 1921-1956
  - General (Box 3)
    - Annual reports
      - 1921-1922 (Folder 3)
      - 1923-1924 (Folder 4)
      - 1925-1926 (Folder 5)
      - 1927-1928 (Folder 6)
      - 1929-1930 (Folder 7)
      - 1932-1934 (Folder 8)
      - 1935-1936 (Folder 9)
      - 1937 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - 1941-1943 (Folder 2)
    - Final reports
      - American Advanced Fellows in Belgium, 1938-1939 (Folder 3)
      - American Advanced Fellows, Visiting Scientist, in Belgium, 1937-1938 (Folder 4)
      - Belgian Fellows in America
        - 1924-1925 (Folder 5)
        - 1925-1926 (Folder 6)
        - 1932-1933 (Folder 7)
        - 1934-1935 (Folder 8)
      - Belgian Visiting Scientists, Advanced Fellows, Graduate Fellows in the U.S., 1938-1939 (Folder 9)
    - Preliminary reports
      - American Fellows in Belgium
        - 1923-1924 (Folder 10)
        - 1924-1925 (Folder 11)
      - American Visiting Lecturers, Advanced Fellows, Grants-in-Aid, in Belgium, 1938-1939 (Folder 12)
      - Belgian Advanced Fellows, Graduate Fellows, in the U.S., 1938-1939 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Belgian Fellows in America
        - 1922-1923 (Folder 2)
        - 1926-1927 (Folder 3)
        - 1927-1928 (Folder 4)
        - 1933-1934 (Folder 5)
        - 1935-1936 (Folder 6)
  - "Belgian and American Advanced Fellows, Graduate Fellows, Special Fellows in the U.S., Belgium and Belgian Congo," 1956 (Folder 7)
  - "Belgian and American Visiting Lecturers, Advanced Fellows, Graduate Felows, Grants-in-Aid, in the U.S. and Belgium," 1949 (Folder 8)
  - "Record of Belgian and American C.R.B. Fellows," 1920-1925 (Folder 9)
  - "Record of Belgian and American C.R.B. Fellows, Visiting Professors, Lecturer, and Scientists," 1920-1936 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "Summer Stipend Holders, University Summer Cources in the History of Flemish Art and Modern Belgian Art," 1938 July-August (Folder 2)
- CLIPPINGS, 1928-1947
  - Belgium - History - German occupation, 1940-1945 (Box 6, Folder 3-6)
  - Belgium - History - German occupation, 1940-1945 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Louvain University Library, 1928-1933 (Folder 2-3)
  - Pierlot, Hubert (Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 5)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS, 1930s(?)
  - Flemish flags, 1930(?) (Folder 8)
  - Education, health and nutrition
    - Questionnaires
    - Statistics
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1915-1941
  - 3 prints depicting the C.R.B. reunion in Brussels, 1934 (Envelope A)
  - 2 prints depicting bomb damage at the Louvain University Library, 1941 (Envelope B)
  - 1 print of the Brussels staff of the C.R.B. (Envelope *mC)
  - 1 print depicting the ship "Camino" docked at Rotterdam, 1915 (Envelope *mD)
  - 3 prints depicting war damage to the city of Vetrmont (Envelope mE)